[Music]
hi everyone welcome back to another
episode of the usada pitch given the
recent introduction of the new blood ABP
modules following years of research and
development we wanted to provide some
insight into blood testing in general
and its role in an effective anti-doping
program the best person to provide that
Insight is Dr Laura Lewis you Saw's
director of science Laura is going to
tell us more about the who when and why
of blood testing okay Laura let's start
with the basics why do we need
blood well Avery it would be really
great if we could test for all
prohibited substances and methods in one
sample type but unfortunately we can't
there are certain substances that can
only be tested for using blood such as
human growth
hormon in addition the athletes
biological passport also requires blabs
and that's needed to longer opportunely
track changes in specific blood values
such as hemoglobin concentration in
particular
side and we have a really good
understanding of the normal variation of
these markers so if we see specific
patterns they may indirectly point to
blooding gotcha so does you do blood
testing on all
athletes we certainly could collect
blood from all athletes but the
frequency of blood collection is
intentionally different for each athlete
some athletes might be blood tested
several times a year whereas others
might only have blood collected once or
twice in their all three so that's a
that's a big difference how does usada
determine who's G to get that blood
testing yeah good question now there are
several different factors that go into
this so firstly under the water code
we're required to collect a certain
number of lessons from athletes in
specific po these are necessary both to
establish to maintain a qu the passport
but also to perform certain types of
analys so we also assigned our testing
accoring factors such as the sport the
level of the athlete retirement of
season and the type of analysis we are
testing athletes in endurance
disciplines can expect somewhat regular
blood testing as part of their
ADP strength and power based Sports
might also notice an increase in blood
testing following the launch of these
new ABP modules that you mentioned
earlier because we need to collect a
series of tests to establish a baseline
profile of each other and finally blood
testing can also occur in competition
either before competition or after the
event
itself awesome are there different types
of blood
testing yes so if not PL is blood tested
uh they'll notice that that bco will
collect different number and or color of
tubes on different
occasions so the lavender or the purple
top tube such as this one um that's
collected primarily for the blood module
of the
ABC you'll notice that these tubes
appear to have contain really small
droplets on the inside and that is
totally normal uh the tubes are sprayed
with an anti plotting agent so the blood
stays in liquid form which is necessary
for uh the analysis in the lab the other
type of tube uh the gold top tubes uh
also known as serin tubes you'll notice
these tubes contain some gel at the
bottom and that's used to separate the
red cells from the serum gold tubes are
used for a number of special analysis
including testing for EPO and grow fors
these tubes are also necessary for the
markers required for the new steroid and
in Define ABC modules so athletes who
previously weren't blood tested that
often they might start to see these gold
tubes a bit more regular so regardless
of the tube collected the blood should
always be collected uh by a certified
lobotomist and be sealed securely in the
sample
of and I did want to add that our dcos
and bcos are trained to make the blood
collection process as comfortable and
minimally invasive as possible but
whilst an athlete can't refuse a blood
test if they do have any concerns about
providing blood samples they really
should be sure to discuss their concerns
with the
dco awesome really good to know thanks
for all the great information Laura
that's it for now but we'll be back with
another episode
[Music]
soon